<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://erinjohnson.space/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://erinjohnson.space/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-18T01:51:37+00:00</updated><id>https://erinjohnson.space/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Erin Johnson&apos;s personal website and blog on computational biology, programming, and science. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">what getting my wisdom teeth out taught me about anesthesia</title><link href="https://erinjohnson.space/blog/2025/what-anesthesia-taught-me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what getting my wisdom teeth out taught me about anesthesia"/><published>2025-12-28T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-28T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://erinjohnson.space/blog/2025/what-anesthesia-taught-me</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://erinjohnson.space/blog/2025/what-anesthesia-taught-me/"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of days ago, I had all four of my wisdom teeth removed. I still remember timidly walking into the surgical room, being wrapped with a heated blanket, and getting plugged in with an oxygen supplement. It was nerve-wracking at first, but (thank god) it went great.</p> <p>Right before the surgery began, I was hooked up to an IV line that delivered anesthesia into my bloodstream. The surgeon told me she calls the anesthesia “vacation” for kids, and “happy hour” for adults. I thought that was pretty funny.</p> <p>For me, it felt like a giant black hole in my memory. I remember when the surgeon administered the first shot, and I remember asking how long it would take me to fall unconscious. Ironically, that’s the last thing I remember before completely blacking out. A small pouch of liquid could completely knock me out. According to my mom, it was like I fell asleep, except I wouldn’t answer when she called my name.</p> <p>But this was nothing like sleep.</p> <p>According to MIT Professor Emery Brown, anesthesia is a “drug-induced, controlled, reversible coma.” It’s completely necessary - no anesthesia means unexplainable pain and trauma from surgery.</p> <p>Professor Brown also explained that the symptoms of anesthesia were similar to something else: death. That sounds kind of terrifying, but it’s a good reminder that powerful things come with real risks. The science behind anesthesia is still pretty foggy, but future breakthroughs could help a lot of other fields. Scientists might be able to use what we learn to find new therapies for depression, actual comas, and sleep disorders. I think it’s cool that something as routine as getting your wisdom teeth out connects to so many bigger questions about the brain.</p> <hr/> <p><strong>Sources</strong></p> <ul> <li>Brown, E. (2015). <a href="https://www.tedmed.com/talks/show?id=309096">Anesthesia and the dynamics of the mind</a>. TEDMED.</li> <li>Virginia Tech News. (2021). <a href="https://news.vt.edu/articles/2021/04/you-re-not-sleeping--expert-to-explain-neuroscience-of-anesthesi.html">You’re not sleeping: Expert to explain neuroscience of anesthesia</a>.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="science"/><category term="neuroscience"/><category term="medicine"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a small pouch of liquid knocked me out completely]]></summary></entry></feed>